Contact

jagarcia29@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/jagarcia29 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Big-Picture Thinking Quality Control Optimization

Languages

English (Native or Bilingual)
Spanish (Native or Bilingual)
French (Elementary)

Certifications

Google Cloud Certified Professional Cloud Architect

Javier Garcia

Cloud and Data Technology Leader

Greater Madrid Metropolitan Area

Summary

Experienced software engineering leader and entrepreneur, specialized in systems integration, process automation, data, and Al. Passionate about the impact of technology and products on business success and society. Experienced designing and scaling complex data and Al driven products.

Specialties:

Business: Innovation, Strategy, Ideation, Sales Engineering Cloud & DevOps: AWS, Google Cloud, Terraform, Ansible, Docker, Gitlab CI, CircleCI, Airflow

Computer Languages: JavaScript, Node.js, SQL, Python, Java, C/C++, HTML, CSS

Data and Modeling: Looker, dbt, Spark, Databricks, Amplitude, MATLAB, Minitab, Tableau, IBM Rational Rhapsody Project Management Tools: Asana, Notion, JIRA, Microsoft Project,

Trello, Slack, Confluence

Foreign Languages: Native proficiency in Spanish

Experience

Mayan

Co-Founder & CTO
July 2020 - Present (4 years 6 months)

Growth automation software for Amazon sellers.

YC W21

Clara Consulting

Founder & Partner

April 2017 - Present (7 years 9 months)

At Clara, we empower startups, scaleups and other data driven busineeses conquer their Cloud, Data and Al Challenges

Data Driven

Lead Data & Cloud Engineer April 2017 - Present (7 years 9 months)

- Lead team of software, data and DevOps engineers, on AWS, GCP, and Azure
- Design and develop ETL projects using Spark Scala, AWS EMR, Databricks, Airflow, DBT, Prefect, and various data sources and warehouses e.g.
 PostgreSQL, MySQL, Snowflake, and BigQuery.
- Design data models on top of SQL databases, optimizing for performance and visualizing Business Intelligence analysis.
- Coordinate and execute cloud infrastructure changes and migrations using Terraform and Ansible.
- Manage serverless architectures using the Serverless framework
- Set up and migrate CI/CD using CircleCI, Gitlab CI, and AWS Code* services.

Qipo

Co-Founder, Data & Integrations Architect April 2015 - March 2018 (3 years)

Greater Boston Area

- Lead strategy and operations, including product and technology roadmaps, recruiting/hiring, and project management.
- Architect and build integrations layer for all external APIs, starting with emails via SendGrid, SMS via Twilio, events and calendars via Google Calendar and Outlook, and custom databases via Quickbase.
- Developing investor pitch decks, business plan and financial model.
- Conducting primary and secondary market research, on-boarded first major customer, and started sales funnel.

MITRE

Software Systems Engineer, Sr. August 2011 - March 2017 (5 years 8 months) Bedford. Ma

- Work closely with Department of Defense stakeholders to develop requirements, evaluate designs, and present progress.
- Built integrations for multiple software platforms and prototypes to enable cross-platform and cross-domain interoperability, and extend overall capability of these systems.
- Developed multiple Java, and HTML/CSS/Javascript prototypes and integrated them with existing legacy systems, simulation tools, and executable models.

- Implemented multiple radar models and simulation test beds using MATLAB
- Implemented C++ versions of MATLAB algorithms, and their accompanying test beds
- Developed UML Models of large-scale systems and data models, using IBM Rational Rhapsody, and Enterprise Architect.
- Setup and manage project and software management processes using JIRA

Covered Security Strategy Consultant May 2016 - August 2016 (4 months)

Greater Boston Area

- Worked directly with CEO in doing primary market research for the consumer side of their product.
- Conducted 500+ online surveys, 20 phone interviews, and corresponding data analysis and visualization.
- Presented results and proposed corresponding business and product strategy recommendations.

White Whale Laboratories COO, Founder February 2011 - September 2011 (8 months) Cambridge, Ma

My role was multi-faceted: the engineer working on our first prototype, the manager, making sure our team was on track and motivated, or the entrepreneur, looking for funding opportunities and driving the business forward.

MIT Space Systems Laboratory
Avionics Team Lead
February 2010 - May 2011 (1 year 4 months)

- -Design, implement, and test the avionics sub-system of the Exoplanet Satellite.
- -Coordinate and prepare presentations for system level reviews throughout the project's development process.
- -Implement image processing and centroiding algorithms on a Xilinx Spartan-3 FPGA.
- -Analyze risks in the subsystem, and design and implement corresponding mitigation strategies and test plans.

MIT Kavli Institute for Astrophysics and Space Research

Digital Hardware and Software Engineer (Transient Exoplanet Survey Satellite)

September 2010 - March 2011 (7 months)

Use ML507 development board with Virtex-5 FPGA to develop image processing routines and implement interfaces with the data handling unit
Install LynxOS Real Time Operating System (RTOS) on ML507 board and set up network connectivity.

MIT Lincoln Laboratory

Engineering Intern (Engineering Analysis Group) June 2010 - August 2010 (3 months)

- -Characterized and calibrated gimbal motors that will control the coarse pointing of the optical communication telescope used on the space terminal of the Lunar Laser Communication Demonstration.
- -Measured rotation angles of the motors using a Coordinate Measuring Machine, and autocollimators.
- -Automated measurements and data collection.
- -Performed data reduction, analyzed data, and created preliminary error correction model.

Agnitio

Software Research and Development Intern May 2009 - August 2009 (4 months)

- -Researched and tested performance of existing scalable distributed and parallel computing frameworks.
- -Speeded up time-intensive training and research scripts by using two different scalable clustering platforms.
- -Integrated MATLAB's Parallel Computing and Distributed Computing Server Toolboxes to work in a server cluster using the Sun Grid Engine resource manager.
- -Generated Java classes from MATLAB scripts using the MATLAB Compiler Toolbox.
- -Integrated the generated Java classes with Hadoop Map-Reduce and Hadoop Distributed File System.

MIT Human and Automation Lab

Research Assistant (Interruption Recovery in Time-critical Supervisory Tasks)

February 2009 - May 2009 (4 months)

- -Validated the Interruption Recovery Assistant integrated into the interfaces used in UAV time-critical supervisory control tasks by performing human experiments, and analyzing behavioral data.
- -Designed scenarios and experimental set-up.

MIT Undergraduate Practice Opportunities Program (UPOP) Participant

October 2008 - May 2009 (8 months)

- -Participated in year-long program that emphasizes professional development and engineering effectiveness.
- -Worked with mentors from industry and faculty from the Sloan School of Management and the School of Engineering on communication, negotiation, presentation, teamwork skills, estimation, decision-making, specifications, and product design.

MIT Human and Automation Laboratory

11 months

Research Assistant (Resource Allocation) September 2008 - December 2008 (4 months)

-Processed and analyzed performance and strategy data collected during human supervisory control experiments from videos, performance records, and mouse clicks logs.

Research Assistant

February 2008 - August 2008 (7 months)

- -Validated the Modified Cooper-Harper for Unmanned Vehicle Displays (MCH-UVD) through experimentation
- -Co-authored the experiment protocol
- -Learned to use Microsoft Flight Simulator, and USARSim, an Unmanned Ground Vehicle simulator.
- -Administered experiment to 30+ participants: recruited participants and trained them to use USARSim.

Education

Massachusetts Institute of Technology
Bachelor of Science, Aerospace Engineering with Information
Technology · (2007 - 2011)

Tufts University

Master's Degree, Engineering Management · (2015 - 2017)

Naples High School High School Diploma · (2003 - 2007)